<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The strong man armed cast out and his goods spoiled, or, The poor man sitting at Jesus's feet clothed and in his right mind being a true convert's testimony of the power of the Lord in turning the soul from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan unto God ... / formerly given forth in writing unto my relations and acquaintance the professors called Independents in Nottinghamshire, declaring the cause of my leaving their assemblies ... by James Jackson, formerly a parish priest and a teacher amongst the Independents and now ... made willing to take up the daily cross and walk with the despised followers of the Lamb in scorn called Quakers.</title>
            <author>Jackson, James, fl. 1674-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J75</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34953</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14914298</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14914298</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102894</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46888)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102894)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1572:6 or 2605:1g)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The strong man armed cast out and his goods spoiled, or, The poor man sitting at Jesus's feet clothed and in his right mind being a true convert's testimony of the power of the Lord in turning the soul from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan unto God ... / formerly given forth in writing unto my relations and acquaintance the professors called Independents in Nottinghamshire, declaring the cause of my leaving their assemblies ... by James Jackson, formerly a parish priest and a teacher amongst the Independents and now ... made willing to take up the daily cross and walk with the despised followers of the Lamb in scorn called Quakers.</title>
                  <author>Jackson, James, fl. 1674-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and torn, with print show-through and loss of print; copy at reel 2605:1g lacks preface.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library and Llyfrgell Genedlaethol Cymru/National Library of Wales, Aberystwyth, Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102894:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Strong Man Armed CAST OUT, And his GOODS SPOILED: Or, the Poor Man ſitting at Jeſus's Feet clothed, and in his Right Mind.</p>
            <p>Being a True Convert's Teſtimony of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Lord, in turning the Soul from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God.</p>
            <p>Wherein is clearly manifeſted, that there is Light in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man and Woman, which diſcovers their Conditions, bears a faithful Teſtimony againſt Sin, is the Reprover of all Unbelief and Unrighteouſneſs both in Heart and Life, and is the Mighty Power of God for Salvation to all that believe in it and obey it.</p>
            <p>And herein it is evidently proved, That they are none of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt that Oppoſe this Doctrine; with one infallible Character of the Real Goſpel-Miniſters; and moſt of the weighty Objections anſwered.</p>
            <p>Formerly given forth in Writing unto my Relations and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance, the Profeſſors, called <hi>Independents,</hi> in <hi>Notingham-ſhire;</hi> declaring the juſt Cauſe of my leaving their Aſſemblies. Together with a tender Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all the Honeſt-hearted, to come out of their <hi>dead Forms,</hi> and walk in the <hi>Light of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> James Jackſon, <hi>formerly a Pariſh Prieſt, and a Teacher amongſt the</hi> Independents; <hi>and now through the exceeding Riches of God's Love, am made willing to take up the Daily Croſs, and walk with the deſpiſed Followers of the Lamb, in Scorn called</hi> Quakers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is a Marvelous Thing, O ye Prieſts, and Profeſſors, that ye know not whence he is, and yet he hath opened mine Eyes. Was it ever known, that ever any man opened the Eyes of one that was born blind?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102894:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102894:2"/>
            <head>TO My Loving Friends, Kindred, AND ACQUAINTANCE; The <hi>Tender, Sober</hi> and <hi>Conſcientious Profeſſors</hi> amongſt the People call'd <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,</hi> in the County of NOTTINGHAM.</head>
            <p>THe Scriptures declare of a Man which had an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean Spirit, who had his dwelling among the Tombs, and no man could bind him, no not with Chains; becauſe he had been often bound with Chains and Fetters, and the Chains had been plucked aſunder by him, and the Fetters broken in pieces; And being dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Devil into the Wilderneſs, he was ſo unruly and fierce, tearing his Cloaths, and cutting his Fleſh, that no man could tame him: But after the Lord Jeſus had healed this poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and effected ſuch an extraordinary Change, as cauſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment and Admiration in the Beholders; for it is ſaid, That when they who had known him before, now ſaw ſuch a palpable Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, he that was called <hi>Legion</hi> Sitting, and Cloathed, and in his Right Mind, they were afraid: and Jeſus ſaid unto him, <hi>Go home to thy Friends, and tell them how Great Things the Lord hath done for thee, and hath had Compaſſion on thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102894:3"/>And truly Friends, this day in my Particular is this Scripture fulfilled in your Eyes; my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, Diſſolute, Debauched and Extravagant Courſe of Life hath been known to moſt of you, when I ſinned after ſtrong Convictions, ſerious Admonitions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, Vows, Promiſes and Reſolutions, againſt known Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Rules, Inward Light and Religious Education, breaking and violating all theſe Bonds and Obligations (which as ſo many Chains and Fetters one would think might be ſufficient to tame and reſtrain the unruly Luſts of Youth) whereby the Souls of ſome of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt and chiefeſt of you have been grieved, exceedingly wounded and exerciſed, endeavouring and earneſtly travelling with Prayers and Tears for my Recovery. Wherefore ſeeing the Lord hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by me when I was in my Blood, and pittied me, and ſaid unto me, <hi>Live;</hi> For it was the Lord only who ſaw my Way, and healed me, and reſtored Comforts to me and my Mourners by the effectual Calling of his Grace, <hi>REVEALING HIS SON IN ME,</hi> and hath ſpared me as a Living Monument of his Patience, Endleſs Mercy and Compaſſion: I therefore in the powerful Conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this Love, am unwilling to eat my Morſel alone, or to hide my Talent in the Earth; but with <hi>Sampſon,</hi> having taſted ſome Sweetneſs and Strength from the Lord, do commend my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences unto you my Friends and Relations, declaring unto you how great Things the Lord hath done for me, and had Compaſſion on me, in turning me from Darkneſs into his Marvellous Light, and from the power of Satan into the Kingdom of his dear Son; To whom be Glory, Praiſe and Obedience for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Jackſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102894:3"/>
            <head>THE Strong Man Armed CAST OUT, And His Goods Spoiled, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN the time of my greateſt Pollution and Iniquity, while I fulfilled the Luſts of the Fleſh with Greedineſs, for many years before that Change and Reformation was diſcerned in me at which ye rejoyced, even in the worſt of my time; I teſtifie in the Preſence of the Lord, that then I met with real and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Reproofs, Rebukes and Convictions from ſomething that did often Awaken, Judge and Condemn me in my own Conſcience, but knew not what it was, nor whence it came; and becauſe Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity was riſen in me to an exceeding maſterleſs height, theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes which I know were from a contrary Principle to Sin, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed not, although at ſome times they were as Powerful and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible as the Hand-Writing upon the Wall before <hi>Belſhazzer,</hi> whereby my Countenance hath been changed, my Thoughts trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, ſo that the Joynts of my Loins were loſed, and my Knees ſmote one againſt another; then thought I to redreſs this Sorrow by going into Merry and Pleaſant Company, eſſaying to divert that inward Perplexity by outward Jollaty, as Drinking, Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Muſick, &amp;c. but thoſe Diverſions were unable to ſtill and quiet theſe Tempeſtuous Surging Waves, and were no more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to heal the Wound of my Sin-ſmitten Conſcience, then if a man ſhould endeavour to quench Fire by pouring Oyl thereon; for I found by woful Experience, that theſe unwarrantable Courſes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102894:4"/>
encreaſed the Flame, and added yet more Weight to the firſt Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: Then have I many times ſolemnly vowed, promiſed and reſolved, To break off and ceaſe from all Ungodly Practices; and in keeping and obſerving theſe Covenants I have found ſome Eaſe and Quietneſs for a time; but as ſoon as new Sins were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then aroſe freſh Occaſions of Sorrow, Trouble and Terror; and after this manner I continued many years, until the Lord was pleaſed of his infinite Wiſdom and Faithfulneſs to hedge up my Way with Remarkable and Extraordinary Providences, blaſting all Purpoſes and Deſigns, and cauſed Afflictions, Loſſes and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments to come upon my outward Eſtate, Horror and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity upon my Soul, a moſt Violent and Raging Feaver upon my Body, and at the ſame time above an Hundred Miles from all Relations, Friends and Kindred; at which time, being in a moſt Wretched, Deplorable and Succourleſs Condition, ſinn'd my ſelf almoſt out of all the Comforts of this Life, and any Hope of Intereſt in a better; being under this great Diſtreſs, and caſt out to the loathing of my own Perſon, and had all my Sins ſet in order before me, whereupon I was forced ſeriouſly to conſider my Wayes, and found no place to eſcape the Wrath of the Highly-provoked God; at which time I had no Benefit of any Outward Help, Teaching or Counſel; but he, who before had been my Reprover, was then my only Teacher, who ſealed Inſtruction upon my Soul, whoſe Voice I heard, which did ſhake and ſhake the Heavens, and the Earth alſo; and cauſed me to cry out, <hi>Lord, What wouldeſt thou have me to do?</hi> And being brought to the Foot of God, could truly ſay, <hi>Speak now Lord, for thy Servant heareth:</hi> And abiding in this broken and ſhattered State, I clearly felt the Judgment of the Lord powerfully at work in my Soul, as an Ax at the Root of the Tree, and as a Refiner's Fire, till the Life and Power of Sin was ſlain, ſubdued and mortified perfectly in my Will and Affections; then was the Lord Jeſus revealed in me whom I had pierced; the New Birth Diſcerned, which is created after God in true Holineſs; and the Immortal, Pure, Precious Seed, of the Eternal God, which ever before had been preſſed down, trodden under and held in Bondage, aroſe; yea, the Tender Plant of his own Right Hand ſprung up in me, panting and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently breathing after, and never ſince could be ſatisfied but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102894:4"/>
with his Living Preſence. Behold! theſe things worketh the Lord oftentimes with men, looking upon men; And if any ſay, <hi>I have ſinned, and perverted that which is Right, and it profitted me not,</hi> he will deliver his Soul from going into the Pit, and his Life ſhall ſee the Light. And this is the Sum of the Confeſſion which I was not aſhamed to witneſs in your publick Aſſemblies, both at <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham</hi> and other places, in the year 1668.</p>
            <p>Objection. But it is probable ſome of you will object, ſaying, <hi>After this Change was wrought, thou didſt Joyn to our Aſſemblies, Owned us, Prayed with us, Preached amongſt us, and ſeemed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy Refreſhings and Satisfaction in our Aſſemblies; wherefore then art thou now departed from us, and gone to the</hi> Quakers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. Notwithſtanding that great and notable Work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in my Soul, and in ſome meaſure effected by the Mighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Lord, yet was there after ſome time a certain Deadneſs, Coldneſs and Darkneſs drawn over me again, occaſioned through Weakneſs, Unwatchfulneſs and Formality, whereby that good Condition was loſt; nevertheleſs I found and felt tender Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings moving in me, thirſting and ſeeking for renewed Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Love of God, then in the Simplicity and Upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Heart, not knowing a more likely way to obtain Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, I joyned to your Society; and can truly affirm (though I now ſee it was no better then ſeeking the Living among the Dead) that the Lord was pleaſed in the Condeſcenſions of his Love, many times to ſtoop down, and reach forth from the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his Boſom Refreſhings and Nouriſhment to that tender Babe of his own begetting, yea, while I frequented your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. And as I continued Faithful and Obedient to that meaſure of Light and Knowledge, which was revealed in me, it is well known to all, or the moſt of you, what Cenſures, Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and Contradiction, both I and the plain Scripture-Truths, which I declared in your Aſſemblies, ſuffered from many of your Brethren, charging me, That I was leading into <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102894:5"/>
long before I underſtood either by word or Writing what the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> held.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. But however, theſe Cenſures occaſioned a free and impartial Search into the <hi>Quakers</hi> Principle, Doctrine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; for verily, before I was as much afraid of the <hi>Quakers</hi> as ye can be: But ſtanding ſingle in the Will and Counſel of the Lord, deſirous to prove all things and hold faſt that which is good, abandoning all Conſultations with Fleſh, was reſolved to ceaſe from Man, and to cleave unto the Truth, as the Lord ſhould reveal and diſcover the ſame to me, waiting in this Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed, Unprejudiced and Diſ-engaged Frame, examining care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the Principle, Foundation, Doctrine and Practice of this Deſpiſed Holy People, great Clearneſs and Satisfaction aroſe in my Soul; for as Face anſwered Face in a Glaſs, ſo were the Truths delivered by them, owned and embraced by the Witneſs of God in my own Conſcience; and the ſame Spirit, Light, Life and Power, which is manifeſt in them, I came to feel in a meaſure in my own Particular: And yet for all this, before I came to any vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Cloſure with them, I ſate down, and counted the Coſt, and am made willing freely to endure the Croſs, and undergo the World's Reproach and Shame, knowing, that whoever will be Chriſt's Diſciple muſt deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and follow him.</p>
            <p>And truly Friends, the Day of the Lord's Power is come and felt, whereby I am made willing to forſake Fathers and Mothers, Brethren and Siſters, Parſonages and all kind of Eccleſiaſtical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, Friends, Honours, Pleaſures, Profits, Houſes, Lands, Goods, yea, and Life is ſelf, to follow the Lamb, and fall in with his Intereſt, as it is only witneſſed and embraced by and amongſt the Children of Light, by the World called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 4. But if it were poſſible, I deſire to make clear to your Satisfaction, that there was ſufficient Ground for me; and ſo there is for you, who have any Tenderneſs and Breathings in your Souls af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lord, to ſeparate your ſelves from the Tents of thoſe Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men, your Teachers, who are no better then Filthy Dreamers,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102894:5"/>
Blind Guides and Belly Gods, who belch out nothing but Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Lyes, Slanders, Falſe Accuſations and Evil Speeches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and Chriſt, his Wayes, Truth and People; and this I ſee and declare againſt them in the Light: For, verily there is, and I witneſs it, an Honeſt, Gracious, Tender Principle in many of you, called <hi>Independents,</hi> which kindles in you perfect Hatred againſt Sin, and unſatisfied real Breathings and Pantings after the Senſible Living Preſence of the Lord; But your Leaders cauſe you to Err, and ye are ſcattered upon the dark and barren Mountains: And this I teſtifie in the Name of the Living God, That it will be ſo with you while ye follow theſe Wandring Stars, Clouds without Rain, Seducing Spirits, your Paſtors and Teachers, who are Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Wolves and Miniſters of Antichriſt, whom ye ought not to receive into your Houſes, nor bid them <hi>God speed;</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) They are altogether Ignorant of the True God; and all the Knowledge that theſe men pretend to have of the Deity, is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Reading and Hear-ſay; for they will confidently affirm, That <hi>Viſion and Immediate Revelation is ceaſed:</hi> Judge ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what Knowledge theſe men have of God, when the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſay, <hi>No man knows the Father but they to whom the Son reveals him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) They Reproach and deſpiſe Jeſus Chriſt, the only Son of God, of whom the Scriptures witneſs and teſtifie to be the True Light, <hi>which enlightens every man that comes into the World:</hi> But they are not afraid to ſay, <hi>The Light in every man is but a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Light, and at the beſt not able to ſave thoſe who believe in it and obey it.</hi> And to diſcover themſelves more plainly to be the Miniſters of Antichriſt, they are not aſhamed to deny that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh: indeed both they and their Grandmother, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are willing to confeſs that Chriſt <hi>was</hi> come; but the Scripture is plain, That <hi>every Soul that confeſſeth not that Chriſt</hi> is <hi>come in the Fleſh, the ſame is Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) They fear not daily to Blaſpheme the Holy Spirit of God; but call it <hi>A Spirit of Deluſion,</hi> and <hi>A Spirit of Error;</hi> and moſt preſumptuouſly ſay of them that are ſanctified, guided, taught and anointed by the Holy Ghoſt, That <hi>they are led by the Spirit of the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102894:6"/>(4.) They trample under Foot the Blood of the Covenant, counting it a Weak and Unholy Thing, while they impudently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That <hi>the beſt of God's Saints</hi> (yea, if he had no purer Saints then they are) <hi>cannot be free from ſin whilſt they breath upon Earth, when</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> witneſs, <hi>that the Blood of Chriſt cleanſeth from all ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">(5.) They preach another Goſpel: Now the Scripture is plain, That <hi>if any man, or an Angel from Heaven, preach any other Goſpel unto us, then what we have already received, let him be accurſed, Gal.</hi> 1.9. Now how can ye believe that they are Miniſters of the Goſpel, when they know not what the true Goſpel is; For, ſaith Paul, <hi>I certifie unto you, Brethren, that the Goſpel which I preach is not after man; for I neither received it, neither was I taught it of man, but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> But your Teachers deny any ſuch Revelation in theſe dayes; wherefore it is hereby e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that they are Thieves, crept in ſome other wayes, and bring another Goſpel, then that whereof <hi>Paul</hi> was a Miniſter, as he witneſſed to the <hi>Colloſſians,</hi> Chap. 1.23. ſaying. <hi>Be not moved from the Hope of the Goſpel, which ye have heard, and which was preached</hi> IN EVERY CREATURE <hi>under Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> In univerſa creatura.</note> 
               <hi>whereof I</hi> Paul <hi>am a Miniſter. And this is the Word of Faith which we preach, even Chriſt, the Word, who is in thy Heart and in thy Mouth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 10. which all have heard, and the Sound thereof is gone through the whole World: But theſe men labour to pervert the Goſpel, and turn men from it, ſaying, <hi>That the Light of Chriſt in every man's Conſcience is not the Subſtance of the Goſpel, nor the Power of God to Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">(6.) They have indeed a Form of Godlineſs, but want the Power; and well for them if that was the worſt: But they mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and cry up a Form, and utterly reject, deſpiſe, and deny the Power, which is the immortal Seed, Chriſt Jeſus, the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and from ſuch we are commanded to turn away.</p>
            <p>Their Prayers and Sermons are made, contrived, ſtudied and compoſed in their own Time, Wills and Wiſdom; but are Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Life, Power and Spirit of Prayer: and deny that Chriſt ſpeaks in any; which is evident that he doth not ſpeak in them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102894:6"/>They cry up, and plead earneſtly for Water-Baptiſm, which Chriſt never Adminiſtred, Inſtituted or Commanded to be Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred; and yet they call it Chriſt's Ordinance: Some ſaying, <hi>Without this no Salvation;</hi> and the reſt ſay, <hi>With ſuch as wilfully neglect this, have no Communion;</hi> But if they had ever undergone and felt the Powerful, Lively, Purifying and throughly clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Efficacy of the Spirit's Baptiſm, they would know it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, without the Help of their Dead, Cold, Idolized Water-Works.</p>
            <p>They are greatly affected with that Bread and Wine, which after breathing upon by the Paſtor, is not Common, but Be-ſaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo comes to be called the Lord's Supper: It is evident hereby, that they never did eat of that Fleſh which is Bread indeed, nor drink of that Blood which is Drink indeed.</p>
            <p>Now it is certain, that all Pictures, Images, Shadows, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances, Figures and Repreſentations, which any people live in and plead for, do clearly argue, That they are deſtitute of the Power, Life and Subſtance, yea, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely ignorant of his Living Preſence, in whom is hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: And as they believe in one at a great Diſtance from them, out of their View and Knowledge; ſo is it very conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, they think, to neceſſitate theſe Carnal Ordinances to reduce their unmindful and forgetful Thoughts into more ſerious Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, till he come: And yet theſe men will condemn the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> though they be far ſhort of their Devotion in this very Thing.</p>
            <p>And ſo are they ſeen in the Light to be Wolves in Sheep's Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ravened from the Life and Power of thoſe Saints, whom they are imitating upon the Stage of their Formal Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, my dear Frieds, Come out from amongſt them, and be ye ſeparate, leſt ye be drunk with the Wine of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication; For verily, the Lord is riſen to plead his own Cauſe, and be a ſwift Witneſs againſt theſe Sorcerers, who are ſporting themſelves in the day time: And as thoſe Souldiers regarded not a Crucified Jeſus ſo near them, but their Minds were taken up in parting &amp; caſting Lots for his Raiment; ſo theſe men are ſo exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Out-ſides of Religion, Ordinances (ſo called) and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102894:7"/>
Worſhip, that they are not at all concerned with the In-ſide, which is the Life and Power of Godlineſs, even Chriſt within, the Hope of Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 5. And Laſtly; As I have plainly declared the Reaſons of my departing from your Aſſemblies, ſo ſhall I witneſs faithfully to the Truth, as it is known and practiſed by the Holy People of God, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> with whom I now walk, and of whom I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and teſtifie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they are built and rooted in &amp; upon the Right Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, even Chriſt Jeſus, the Lord; who is their Wiſdom, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption, in whom alone they are juſtified by Faith, and ſaved.</p>
            <p>That Root from whence they receive Life, Nouriſhment, Pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er and Growth, is the only Foundation of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles, the Rock of Ages, the Stone which your Builders and thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Brethren, the Prieſts, ever rejected, diſallowed and ſet at nought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is, <hi>Chriſt in us, the Hope of Glory.</hi> Whereupon it is evident that we differ in the Root from all the People in the World, though of ſeveral Forms and Perſwaſions: For plainly, the <hi>Papiſts, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Presbyters, Baptiſts</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> though they all differ in their Forms, Appearances, and Circumſtantial Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet do they all agree and meet in one and the ſame Faith, Foundation and Root.</p>
            <p>The Words, Writings, Declarations and Teſtimonies of the Saints, recorded in Scripture, are the Foundation and Ground of all the Profeſſing People in the World; and all of them being Strangers to that one Spirit that gave forth the Scriptures, are run into ſeveral Sects and Opinions, as they do carnally underſtand and conceive they have Rule and Teaching in the Bible: But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they will own no other Light, Law, Goſpel, Rule, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and Word of God, but their Bibles. But now this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar People, whom the Lord hath gathered from amongſt all the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Confuſions and Diviſions under Heaven, are built upon the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner-Stone, in whom all the Building fitly framed together, groweth into an Holy Temple in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102894:7"/>So that theſe receive immediate Light, Life, Power, Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Guidance, Rules, Refreſhings, Revelation, Peace and Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tisfaction from that Word which was before the Worlds were made; even that Life, Power, Foundation, Root, Spring and Fountain, in and by which the Holy Prophets and Apoſtles were Quickened, Enlightened, Anointed, Inſpired, and gave forth the Scriptures, which is Chriſt Jeſus, the Word of God, the Power of God, the Son of God, the Light Within, the only Saviour of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Their Faith is the Faith of the Son of God; Jeſus Chriſt is the Author and Finiſher of it: It is not a Dead Hiſtorical Faith, but the Spirit and Life of Faith, and no leſs then the Reſurrection and Life of the Immortal Seed, Enlightening, Quickening, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and Renewing the whole Man; And this is that Faith by which Sin is ſubdued, ſlain and mortified perfectly, the Heart pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, the World conquered, the Soul ſanctified, juſtified and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved perfectly: But the Faith of all others is an Unholy, Dead, Imperfect Faith; it ſanctifies but in part (as they ſay) and ſo will never ſave to the uttermoſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Their Knowledge is Spiritual and Experimental, from the immediate Unction of the Holy Ghoſt; what is known, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from Hear-ſay, but divine Revelation: All that are born of the Spirit are taught of God, and need not that any ſay, <hi>Know the Lord;</hi> for they all know him, from the greateſt to the leaſt: This is Life Eternal to know God, who is Light, yea, the Father of Lights; and that the Light within is the Son of God, whom he hath ſent; ſo to know as to live and abide in his Light, is Life E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal: And this is that Myſtery which is hid from the Wiſe and Prudent, and is revealed unto Babes; for the World by all its Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knows not God, neither doth the Carnal Man (though never ſo great a Schollar) diſcern the things of God; for they are Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually diſcerned.</p>
            <p>And as Chriſt was Bodily in the World, and the World knew him not, no, not the great Doctors and Leaders of thoſe ſeveral Sects and Religions in that day, as the <hi>Samaritans, Herodians, Scribes, Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces,</hi> they knew him not; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the man that was born blind wondred, <hi>This is a Marvelous
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102894:8"/>
Thing,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that ye know not from whence he is, and yet he hath opened mine Eyes: It was never known that any man opened the Eyes of one that was born blind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo it is now; Chriſt is ſpiritually in the World, and the World knoweth him not; no, not the <hi>Popes, Prelates, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Paſtors</hi> of all the Religions in the World, they know him not, but ſay, <hi>It is the Devil,</hi> or at beſt, <hi>but the Light of Nature;</hi> and ſo they know not from whence he is, yet hath he inlightned Thouſands: And it was never known that the <hi>Devil</hi> or <hi>Nature</hi> converted any to the Lord, that have been Naturalized to Sin.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, Their Humility, which is the emptying of themſelves of all their own Righteouſneſs, Wills, Wiſdom and Self-Exaltation; and is a real, inward, ſpiritual Abaſement and Subjection to the Life, Power &amp; Kingdom of Chriſt Jeſus, manifeſted in Spirit, ruling and dwelling in their mortal Bodies: And ſo this True, Humble, Meek and Low Frame of Spirit proceeds from their experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Knowledge of Chriſt's living Preſence in them; whereas they that know God and Chriſt only by Reading and Hear-ſay, with a Literal and Hiſtorical Knowledge, they are blown, ſwell'd and puffed up with Airy Notions, Vain Boaſtings and Self-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, Their Unity, which conſiſts not only in the Oneneſs of Opinion and Judgment, but proceeds from Unity of Spirit: And their Love one to another is not from a Natural but a Heavenly and Spiritual Principle; It is not the Love of one man to another, but it is the Love of God ſhed abroad in their Hearts, which maketh them all of one Mind, and all ſpeak, write and witneſs the ſame thing: For as the Vital Spirits in the Natural Frame have its Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration through every Member, it makes the Eyes, Ears, Tongue, Hands and Feet, to ſee, hear, ſpeak, work and walk, and yet but one Soul that moves and quickens all through its ſpeedy Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe into every Member and Part of the Body; ſo is it here, the Love, Peace, Concord and Unity amongſt theſe is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; it flows from the Fountain of Love, and influenceth the whole Body, which makes them in all their Wayes, Doctrine and Practice but as One Man: And though but a Poor, Weak, Harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102894:8"/>
Innocent and Inoffenſive People, are rendred through their Unity and Love, as Terrible as an Army with Banners.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, Their Patience is invincible: To them is this Grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Not only to Believe in the Name of Jeſus, but alſo to Suffer for his ſake.</hi> And as the Lord hath made them Bleſſed and Glorious Inſtruments in his Hand to do his Will, ſo hath he made them contented to be perfected through Sufferings: For though the Lord hath been eſpecially preſent with them, yet the World hath been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially againſt them; not for their own ſakes (for they are the only Innocent and Harmleſs People upon Earth) but for Chriſt's ſake in them; yea, becauſe there is more of God among theſe men then others, therefore are they hated of all men, and every where amongſt all Religions evil ſpoken of: for the World moſt hates where there is moſt of God; therefore the Single-hearted may gueſs where there is moſt of God, by obſerving where the greateſt Hatred of the World lies.</p>
            <p n="7">7thly, Their Faithfulneſs to the Truth, Wayes and Intereſt of Chriſt; How have they gone up and down in Wearineſs and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in Hunger and Nakedneſs, in Dangers and Deaths, to bear a Faithful Teſtimony againſt the Sin, Vanity, Falſe Worſhip and Abomination of the Times? When did they ſhrink in the leaſt, or turn back from their Duty, when Loſs of Eſtate, Liberty, yea, Danger of Baniſhment attended it? When did they Deny their Maſter or his Commands, or Betray his Intereſt before King or Counſel Table, Judges, Juſtices or Biſhops, by Subſcribing, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging, Swearing, Bowing or Complying to the Wills and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of men? Nay, they have witneſſed a Good Confeſſion, and ſpoken of his Teſtimonies before all theſe, and were not aſhamed: When did they meet at Night for fear of being ſeen, or creep in at Back-Doors into Cellars, Holes and ſecret Places to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Knowledge of the Adverſary? But the time would fail me to ſpeak of their Self-denyal, Temperance, Sobriety, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, Doctrine, Order, Worſhip, their Spirit of Prayer and Watchfulneſs, Holineſs, Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt: The King's Daughter is all Glorious within, and her Rayment is of pure Gold. Therefore in Truth and Sincerity to them I will ſay, <hi>Who is like unto thee, O People, ſaved by the Lord,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102894:9"/>
the Shield of thy Help &amp; the Sword of thy Excellency? Thine Enemies ſhall be found Lyars unto thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their High Placet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet to make it appear more plain, that this Light within, which indeed is our Principle, is the Truth, and the Mighty Power of God for Salvation to all that believe in it and obey it, will be further ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by its Nature and Effects.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>NATURE</hi> of this Light.</head>
               <p>It is a Living, Immortal, Unchangeable, Undefiled, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and Perfect Principle of pure Holineſs, which never fell, comply'd with, or conſented to any Evil; But hath ever oppoſed and ſtood croſs to the whole corrupt Nature, Will and Affections of faln man: For I know that all <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity are by Nature faln under Guilt, Pollution, Condemnation and Darkneſs. So that the Light I ſpeak of is nothing of Man's Nature, but of the pure Divine Nature, even that Seed promiſed <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. yea, the Son of God, which is ſent into the World, <hi>that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on him ſhould not periſh, but have Eternal Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>EFFECTS</hi> of this Light.</head>
               <p>When Chriſt was upon Earth, <hi>John</hi> ſaw and bare record, <hi>That he was the Lamb of God, which taketh away the Sins of the World:</hi> Yet the Lord ſaid, <hi>A greater Teſtimony have I, then that of</hi> John; <hi>for the Works that I do in my Father's Name, they teſtifie of me:</hi> So ſay we of him now; he is ſpiritually the Light in man, however ſleighted, rejected and undervalued by men; yet is he choſen of God, and pretious, the alone Saviour of the World; and the Works he accompliſhes daily in the Souls and Conſciences of men teſtifie the ſame; wherefore, if his Works be not ſuch as none elſe can do, believe him not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Effect</hi> I. Hereby the Sinner is convinced, judged, reproved and condemned plainly and experimentally, for all the Sins that ever he committeth, of what Kind or Nature ſoever they be: <hi>Come</hi> (ſaid the Woman of <hi>Samaria) and I will ſhew ye a Man that hath told me all things that ever I did;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John.</hi> 4.29.</note> 
                  <hi>is not this the Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:102894:9"/>
                  <hi>Effect</hi> 2. <hi>The Fear of the Lord,</hi> which <hi>is the Beginning of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> is never truly placed in the Heart, till this Principle be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed and owned; for while a Man looks at God and Chriſt at a great Diſtance, circumſcribed in ſome Place beyond the Stars, the Sinner rageth &amp; is confident; but when the Mind &amp; Underſtanding is perſwaded that the Pure, Holy, Righteous, Omnipotent and Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſent Lord God is not only nigh him, but within him alſo, he is then brought into awful Apprehenſion of the moſt High, &amp; forced to cry out with <hi>Job, I have heard of thee before by the Hearing of the Ear, but now mine Eyes have ſeen him:</hi> by this Means the Mind is mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into much Tenderneſs and Brokenneſs, and with the Prophet complaineth, <hi>Wo is me; for I am undone.</hi> Now conſider this all ye that deſpiſe the Light within,<note place="margin">Joh. 9.30</note> 
                  <hi>This is a Marvelous Thing</hi> (ſaid the Young Man) <hi>that ye know not whence he is, and yet he hath opened my Eyes; ſince the World began was it not heard that any Man opened the Eyes of one that was born Blind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Effect</hi> 3. Waiting humbly in this pure Dread &amp; Fear of the Lord, Man's Inſufficiency to anſwer the Requirings of the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment is diſcerned; but perfect Power and Strength in Chriſt the Light, is diſcovered; for indeed, <hi>in him are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge:</hi> and ſtanding up to the Manifeſtation of this Light, the Judgment of the Lord is felt as a <hi>Refiner's Fire,</hi> which throughly purifies, and as <hi>Fullers Soap</hi> that leaves no Spot; then the Soul knows that flaming Sword, which kept faln Man out of Paradiſe; but now diſcerns the new Birth, which bears the Image of the Heavenly Nature; the ſtrong Man armed, which before held Poſſeſſion, Bound, caſting out, and all his Goods ſpoiled by the Powerful Entrance of Chriſt into his Temple.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Effect</hi> 4. Waiting and abiding in this <hi>Light</hi> for Counſel and Teaching, the whole Man being emptyed of his own Will and Wiſdom, ſtanding ſingly and purely in the Will of the Lord, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be diſpoſed, ordered and guided univerſally by the Light, the Soul now thrives in the Fear and Love of God, bringeth forth the peaceable Fruits of Righteouſneſs, and liveth in that Faith which purifies the Heart, and getteth Victory over the World, Sin and Death.</p>
               <p>Theſe Things, with many other which might be mentioned, do make it manifeſt, that whoever deny, deſpiſe and reproach the Light
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102894:10"/>
within, deny God, the Father of Lights, deſpiſe Jeſus Chriſt, the Light &amp; Saviour of the World, and reproach the Holy Spirit which maketh manifeſt and reproveth the Sins of Men: Wherefore all ye Profeſſors that look out for another Saviour, remember the Anſwer of our Lord Jeſus unto <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> upon the like Account, <hi>Art thou he,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>or ſhall we look for another? Go</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and tell him that ſent you, what you have heard and ſeen; the Blind receive their Sight, the Deaf hear, &amp;c.</hi> Even the ſame in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Senſe may be as really affirmed of the <hi>Light within;</hi> hereby have the Eyes, Ears and Mouthes of the Blind, Deaf and Dumb been opened, the Lame, Lepers and the Dead, cured, cleanſed and quickned, and the Poor, whom none of the Proud, Covetous Clergy (ſo called) regardeth, they by Vertue hereof, have the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel preached unto them; and forever bleſſed are they who are not offended in the <hi>Light,</hi> but love it, believe in it, and obey it in all things.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>But we are afraid of being deceived; this is a new and ſtrange Doctrine; did ever Chriſt or his Apoſtles bid Men believe and obey the Light within?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Art thou not already deceived? Conſider therefore well thy Condition, if thou art delivered out of the deceived State, in which the greateſt Part of the World yet remains; art thou yet in a ſinful tranſgreſſed Eſtate? <hi>For the Woman being deceived was in the Tranſgreſſion,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. We that believe and abide in the Light, know that we are not deceived; neither ſeek we to deceive any, neither fear we any deceiving us: though indeed while we walked in the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of our own deceitful Hearts, and warmed our ſelves by the Sparks of our own kindling, that then as the Serpent beguiled <hi>Eve</hi> through his Subtilty, ſo our Minds were corrupted from the Simplicity that is in Jeſus; in which State we ſee many yet to ſtand whom the Lord will undeceive in his own Time; <hi>But Evil Men and Seducers will wax worſe, deceiving and being deceived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. Never fear Deceit in ſuch who turn you to the <hi>Light,</hi> whereby ye may diſcern betwixt Good and Bad, Truth and Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; plainly, I would much fear that he had a Deſign to cheat me, who leads into the <hi>Dark,</hi> and denyes the Benefit of the Light.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:102894:10"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 4. Search with Freedom, and examine throughly this Doctrine, condemn it not unheard, ſpeak not Evil of any Thing unknown; for ſo mayſt thou ſoon condemn the Innocent, and make thy ſelf guilty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 5. Underſtand fully what we hold before thou contend againſt us, leſt if thou want this Patience and Wiſdom, thou oppoſe not ſo much our Judgment as thy own Conceit; better it is to hear a Man's Mind with Meekneſs, then haſtily to gueſs at it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 6. Be not wedded to thy own Opinion, nor Wiſe in thy own Conceit, ſo as to build upon thy own or other Mens Judgments, and reſt ſatisfied therein, becauſe it is ſtrengthned by Multitude, Cuſtom and Antiquity; for undoubtedly many have erred groſly in thoſe Things they have thought themſelves Infallible; better it is to cleave to the clear and naked Truths of God alone, then to follow the Doctrines of the moſt learned and eminent Profeſſors in the World, when they <hi>hold</hi> not <hi>the Truth as it is in Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 7. Reproach not this Doctrine, ſaying, <hi>It is New and Strange,</hi> or that <hi>thou never heardſt it ſo before;</hi> for this diſcovers thy <hi>Ignorance</hi> rather then my <hi>Error:</hi> and that which at preſent ſeems to thee to be a <hi>New Error,</hi> being rightly examin'd by the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> will prove an <hi>Old Truth:</hi> If therefore thou wilt needs reject whatſoever favours of <hi>Novelty,</hi> how ſhall the <hi>Truths we yet know</hi> not be brought in, and the <hi>Ignorance</hi> which yet remains be purg'd out?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 8. This is the ſame Doctrine which was preach'd by our bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> and his holy <hi>Prophets</hi> &amp; <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſince the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and which was believ'd and obey'd by all the faithful Saints and Servants of God ſince the Creation; the ſame which the Lord gave in Charge to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by the Mouth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Behold, I ſend my Angel before thee to keep thee in the Way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 23.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and to bring thee into the Place which I have prepared, Beware of him and obey his Voice; provoak him not, for he will not pardon your Tranſgreſſions, for my Name is in him; but if thou ſhalt indeed obey his Voice, and do all that I ſpeak, then will I be an Enemy to thy Enemies, and an Adverſary to thy Adverſaries.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 15.30.</note> 
                  <hi>But the Soul that doth ought preſumtuouſly, reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the Lord, and ſhall be cut off from his People; becauſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the Word of the Lord.</hi> Now what is this Word of the Lord?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102894:11"/>
It is not the Scriptures; for there were no <hi>Bibles</hi> many Years after that time,<note place="margin">Deut. 30.11. to 14. Pſal. 119.9.105.</note> but the LIGT WITHIN. <hi>It is not hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from thee, neither is it far off; but the Word is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nigh unto thee, even in thy Heart &amp; in thy Mouth, that thou ſhouldſt hear it and do it:</hi> Wherefore <hi>David</hi> affifirmeth, that <hi>if a Young man take heed to this Word, he ſhall cleanſe his Wayes thereby;</hi> and calls it <hi>a Lamp to his Feet, and a Light to his Paths.</hi> This is alſo teſtified by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Thou ſhalt hear a Word behind thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 30.21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaying, This is the Way, walk in it; in which Path the wayfaring Men, though Fools, cannot err.</hi> And our bleſſed Saviour doth confirm this Doctrine,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.35. Lu. 17.21. Acts 3.22. vſ. 23, 26.</note> ſaying, <hi>Seek firſt the Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs;</hi> which <hi>Kingdom</hi> he told the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> was <hi>within</hi> them. Thus <hi>Peter</hi> preacht <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Light; <hi>For</hi> Moſes <hi>truly ſaid unto the Fathers, A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you, him ſhall you hear in all things; and it ſhall come to paſs, that every Soul that heareth not that Prophet, ſhall be cut off, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore unto you firſt God having raiſed up his Son <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſent him to bleſs you in turning every one of you from his Iniquities;<note place="margin">Acts 26.18.</note> and thus <hi>Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was ſent, <hi>To turn men from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God.</hi> Now, is not this <hi>Darkneſs</hi> within, and the <hi>Light</hi> within? And is it not an <hi>inward</hi> Turning,<note place="margin">Acts 17.27.</note> 
                  <hi>To ſeek the Lord, if happily they might f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>el af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him and find him; though he be not far from every one of us?</hi> And doth not <hi>James</hi> turn men to the <hi>Light within,</hi> writing to Sinners,<note place="margin">Jam. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Such as were in Filthineſs and ſuperfluity of Naughtineſs?</hi> Doth not he bid them <hi>receive with Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the ingrafted Word, which was able to ſave their Souls;</hi> which <hi>Peter</hi> calleth the <hi>ſure Word of Prophecy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> 
                  <hi>unto which ye do well to give heed as vnto a Light that ſhineth in a dark Place?</hi> But moſt take the <hi>Word</hi> for the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> but we know no <hi>Word</hi> but <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>his Name</hi> only <hi>is call'd the Word of God:</hi> Therefore, <hi>ſay not in thy Heart, who ſhall bring and reveal Chriſt unto us? for the Word is nigh thee, even in thy Heart and in thy Mouth:</hi> Now this <hi>Word</hi> is <hi>Chriſt, the true Light in every man;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 12.36.</note> wherefore ſaith our Lord Jeſus, <hi>While ye have the Light believe in the Light, that ye may be the Children
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102894:11"/>
of the Light;</hi> As, <hi>Abel</hi> being guided by this Light, <hi>through Faith was enabled to offer up a more acceptable Sacrifice then Cain:</hi> In Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to this Enoch <hi>walked with, and pleaſed God:</hi> By this Noah <hi>being warned, moved with Fear, prepared an Ark for the ſaving of his Houſe:</hi> By this <hi>was</hi> Abraham <hi>called to leave his own Country and his Father's Houſe;</hi> and in Obedience to this <hi>he departed, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether he went: Joſeph</hi> being guided by this, withſtood the Temptations of his <hi>Mrs,</hi> though enforced with Importunity, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Profit &amp; Secreſie: Hereby Moſes <hi>choſe rather to ſuffer Affliction with the People of God, then to enjoy the Pleaſures of Sin for a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, eſteeming the Reproach of Chriſt greater Riches then the Treaſures of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and endured, as ſeeing him that is Inviſible. And what ſhall I ſay more? for the Time would fail to tell of</hi> Gideon, Barak, Sampſon, Jepthah, David, Samuel, <hi>and of the Prophets, who by Faith,</hi> and Obedience to the Light, <hi>ſubdued Kingdoms, wrought Righteouſneſs, obtained Promiſes, ſtopped the Mouths of Lyons, quenched the Violence of Fire: Some were tortured, not accepting Deliverance: Others had Tryal of cruel Mockings, Scourgings, Bonds, and Impriſonment, and Death.</hi> And is ſtill the ſame at this Day; for the <hi>Light within</hi> is the true Shepherd's Voice, which all the Lambs of Chriſt hear, obey and follow, to the Hazard of all that is dear to them.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>But thou denyeſt the Scriptures to be the Word of God, which is the Only Rule to judge of Doctrines, and a ſure Weapon to reſiſt Satan, and confute his Miniſters; for it is very obſervable that Christ made <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of no other Means to overcome the Tempter, but Only the Scriptures, which are the Sword of the Spirit and the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 Plainly, I deny the Scriptures are either the Sword of the Spirit, or the Word of God: That the Word of God is the Sword of the Spirit, I own, and witneſs that it is ſharper then a Two-edg'd Sword, like a Hammer and a Fire, the Ax at the Root of every corrupt Tree, and ſo are not the Scriptures; yea, the Word of the Lord is Unchangeable, Incorruptible and Eternal, without Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Dayes, or End of Time; and ſo are not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Nevertheleſs, we prefer the Holy Scriptures as they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102894:12"/>
were given forth by the Holy Spirit of God, and believe them to be a true Declaration of God and of his Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. Yet do we prefer Chriſt Jeſus the Light, above the Scriptures; for in all Things he muſt have the Preheminence; therefore ſaith <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, I prefer him before me, for he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me,</hi> though in Appearance <hi>John</hi> was ſeemingly before Chriſt; <hi>Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was, I am,</hi> ſaid he: Wherefore know that we build not upon the Holy Prophets and Bleſſed Apoſtles, their Words, Works, Writings and Experiences; but we are built upon the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Foundation and the chief Corner-Stone; ſo that we have not received our Light, Life, Peace, Comfort, Faith, Hope and Aſſurance from the Writings of the Saints, but from him that was their Light, Life, Hope, Root and Foundation, and have our Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from that Light, whereby <hi>Abel, Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> walked with and pleaſed God, long before any Scriptural Rules were manifeſted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 4. Neither are the Scriptures the only Rule to judge of Doctrines; for we know the Scriptures are hard to be underſtood; and therefore Men in their carnal Wiſdom are putting their ſeveral Meanings upon one and the ſame Scripture; wherefore we ſay, the Spirit of God is the only Judge of Doctrines, becauſe he alone that gave forth knows the Meanings of Scriptures;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>For the Spirit ſearcheth all Things; yea, the Deep Things of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 5. Nor yet do I believe that the Scriptures were the only Means which Chriſt made Uſe of to overcome and repel the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Wilderneſs; for we obſerve, Satan pleaded Scripture as well as Chriſt, till he took indeed the Sword of the Spirit, which is his Divine <hi>Power,</hi> and commanded him, ſaying, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan;</hi> then the Devil left him, but not before he was thus expelled.</p>
               <p>Object. 3. <hi>But this Doctrine of the Light within is oppoſed by all the able learned Divines</hi> (ſo call'd) <hi>in the Nation; yea, the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Preachers amongst the</hi> Presbyters, Independents <hi>and</hi> Baptiſts, <hi>do condemn it for Erroneous and Diveliſh Deluſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It's true, this Doctrine hath been and is a Stone of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102894:12"/>
Stumbling, &amp; a Rock of Offence unto all Sorts &amp; Forms of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in the World; eſpecially, the <hi>Prieſts &amp; Preachers</hi> are moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterately incenſed againſt it, becauſe the Craft by which they have gotten great Gain, is hereby eſpecially impared; nevertheleſs, the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt it: the Truth is ſtrong and will prevail, yea, it doth and will flouriſh in Deſpight of all the Scorns, Injuries, Oppoſition and Villany of the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. The Scriptures are plain, that <hi>God hath hid theſe Things from the Wiſe and Prudent</hi> in the World, <hi>and hath revealed them unto Babes: Behold therefore ye Deſpiſers and wonder; for this is the Work which God hath wrought in your Day, which ye will not believe, though it be declared unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. And as for thoſe Preachers among the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> &amp;c. who oppoſe this Doctrine, this I affirm, and teſtifie againſt them, though they come in Sheeps Cloathing (that is) have gotten a more refined Way of Profeſſion then others, and cover themſelves with the Words of the Prophets and Apoſtles, yet inwardly are they Ravening Wolves, they are inwardly Ravened from the Light and Life of thoſe Saints, whoſe Words they have taken up; yea, it is an eaſie Thing to prove againſt the beſt of them, that they live in Sin and plead for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 4. Whoever deny, reproach and oppoſe this Doctrine, are none of Chriſt's Miniſters, as will appear from a due Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their Call, Doctrine and Practice: Who ſent them? God or Man? What do they preach? the Word of God, or the Words of Men? Is their Life and Converſation Humble, Meek, Self-denying and Heavenly? Or is it not Proud, Fierce, Self-ſeeking and Worldly? Now our Lord Jeſus hath left upon Record one Infallible Rule, whereby we may know which are true Goſpel-Miniſters, and which are not: and as it is granted, that Chriſt was a true Goſpel-Miniſter; ſo it is expected, that all Goſpel-Miniſters be like him in their Meaſure; for ſaith Chriſt to his Father, <hi>As thou ſent me into the World, ſo have I ſent them into the World,</hi> Joh. 17. And when he ſent forth his Diſciples, to them he ſaith, <hi>As the Father ſent me, even ſo ſend I you.</hi> Hereby then it will eaſily be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, that theſe Preachers, who ſo bitterly Rage and Rail againſt the <hi>Light within,</hi> are never an one of them Chriſt's Miniſters, but Idol-Shepherds, Lyars and Falſe Prophets.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:102894:13"/>
                  <hi>Qualification</hi> 1. Chriſt was the Son of God, and known to be ſo before he undertook or exerciſed in the Miniſtry, for the Lord fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeing what after came to paſs by Peoples running into ſeveral Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Doctrines of men, gave this Charge and Teſtimony from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed, hear him:</hi> In like manner every true Believer is a <hi>Son of God,</hi> generated of the immortal Seed, born anew by the Operation of the Spirit, made a real Partaker of the Divine Nature, liveth in and hath Union with God through Faith in Chriſt; for <hi>to as many as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him he giveth Power to become the Sons of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qualif.</hi> 2. He was immeaſurably anointed with the Spirit, and was known to be ſo; for ſaith <hi>John, He that ſent me to baptize, the ſame ſaid unto me, On whomſoever thou ſhalt ſee the Spirit deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and remaining, the ſame is he;</hi> So may true <hi>Goſpel-Miniſters</hi> be known, for they are as really anointed with the Holy Spirit of God, as Chriſt was, though not ſo equally; yea every believing Soul is indued with this Spirit; theſe are the Anointed ones of the Lord; and whoever want this Spirit, <hi>they are none of his:</hi> And as Chriſt commanded his Diſciples <hi>to abide at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>till they had received this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction;</hi> ſo whoever undertake to preach before they have receiv'd this Power from the Lord, they Run and he ſent them not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qualif.</hi> 2. He endured and conquered the Aſſaults and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Satan in the Wilderneſs, by virtue of his Sonſhip and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, before he was ever known to preach the Goſpel; in like manner all the true Children of God are taken into Fellowſhip with Chriſt in his Tryals, Temptations and Sufferings; but eſpecially ſuch as have been call'd unto more eminent &amp; publick Work, have met with greateſt Conflicts, Wraftlings and Temptations, that they might be kept humble before the Lord, and alſo be fitly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſpeak a Word in due ſeaſon for the Relief of ſuch as are brought under the ſame Trouble.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qualif.</hi> 4. In the Power, Virtue and Strength of his Son-ſhip, Unction and Conqueſt, he went out and preached the Goſpel, that is, proclaimed Glad Tidings of the Grace and Good-will of God to the Poor, and preached Peace to the Broken-hearted, teſtifying the Love of God to Mankind, in ſending his Son to them to open their Blind Eyes, and recover them out of the Snare of the Devil;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102894:13"/>
exhorting Men to believe in the Light, leſt Eternal Darkneſs come upon them: And all that was done in his Miniſtry, was not from any outward Encouragement or Reward, but moved only hereunto from the Tenderneſs of his Pitty and Compaſſion to poor Sinners. So it is at this Day, all that are born of the Spirit are true Miniſters of the ſame Goſpel, and publiſh it freely in the Conſtrainings of the Love of God, which layes a Neceſſity upon them to miniſter freely without Expectation of Gifts and Rewards: But do they deſerve the Name of Goſpel-Miniſters, who preach another Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine then what Chriſt or his Apoſtles ever did, confidently affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>That the Doctrine of the Light within, or to ſay, the Light in every Man's Conſcience is the Light of Chriſt, this is Blaſphemy; but tell Men, that Light which doth convince them of Sin is not the Light of Chriſt, but Natural Conſcience, and therefore not able to ſanctifie and ſave ſuch as believe in it and obey it?</hi> and yet they ſay, <hi>There be ſome whom they call Saints and Believers, in whom there is true Saving Light; but as for the greatest Part of the VVorld, they are altogether deſtitute hereof:</hi> and yet though they make a ſeeming Diſtinction between Saints and Sinners, yet they themſelves confeſs <hi>they are Sinners;</hi> yea, and believe <hi>that they muſt be ſo while they breath upon Earth:</hi> And thus are People held in Ignorance, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief and Confuſion, their blind Guides having cauſed them to err from the Truth; for verely this hath been and is the Doctrine of theſe eminent Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qualif.</hi> 5. That Goſpel which Jeſus Chriſt had preached, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed to in his holy Life, he confirmed and ſeal'd by his Death in his Blood: Now this Laſt is that which crowned and compleated his Miniſtry; and the ſame Spirit is in all the Faithful at this day, whereby Chriſt's Miniſters are enabled to declare the Truth in the Life and Power of the Eternal Word, without the Help and Aſſiſtance of acquired Parts, Arts and Studies; for to ſuch ſaith Chriſt, <hi>It is not you that ſpeak, but the Spirit which ſpeaketh in you;</hi> and thus declaring what they have ſeen, taſted and handled of the Word of Life, they are not aſhamed of their Work, nor afraid of Men; neither will they conceal their Meetings in Time of greateſt Danger, nor ſlip out at Back-Doors to avoid Sufferings; but are in a continual Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs and Preparedneſs to forſake all that is dear to them, rather then to turn their Backs upon the Work of God, or in the leaſt to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102894:14"/>
prove Unfaithful by Denying or Betraying the Truths of Chriſt: Wherefore now conſider theſe things all ye <hi>Admirers of Men,</hi> and give place to the <hi>Witneſs of God in your own Conſciences,</hi> and ſee if one of your Gifted Brethren, Paſtors and Teachers be thus qualified.</p>
               <p>Object. 4. <hi>But the Scriptures are very plain, that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers and Reprobates are without Chriſt, as in</hi> Epheſ. 2.12. <hi>and</hi> 2 Cor. 13 5. <hi>wherefore though we do believe, that Christ is in every Believer, yet we cannot understand that the Light in every Man is the Light of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Indeed one of theſe Scriptures at firſt Appearance, ſeems to contradict all that hath been ſaid before, it will be therefore neceſſary to ſpeak to them ſeverally. That in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. plainly affirms, That before Converſion <hi>they were without God, and without Christ in the World:</hi> And truly, I can witneſs this Scripture fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in my own Particular; for I know the Time when I was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, and without God in the World, when I lived in Sinful Pleaſures and Delights, fulfilling the Luſts of the Fleſh with Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs; I lived then as if there was no God in the World, yea, without any awful Reſpect to the Eye of God and Chriſt; And yet I can as truly affirm, that at that Time the Light of Chriſt was in me teſtifying againſt my Iniquity: And this may ſeem a Myſtery that a Meaſure of his Light ſhould be within a Man, when that Man is without Chriſt; yet I have experienced the Truth hereof, and therefore teſtifie, that its one Thing for the Light of Chriſt to be in a Man, and another Thing for a Man to be in the Light of Chriſt; and thus it is, the Light of Chriſt may be in a Man, and yet that Man out of the Light of Chriſt; whereupon I affirm and declare, that the Light of Chriſt is in every Man; but no Man is in Chriſt till he be a new Creature.</p>
               <p>And as to that other Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Know ye not your own ſelves, how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except ye be Reprobates.</hi> This Place doth not at all oppoſe what before hath been written, if it be ſeriouſly conſidered, but doth greatly confirm the Truth of this Doctrine: If therefore by <hi>Reprobates</hi> be intended ſuch as have ſinned out the Day of Grace, and done Deſpight to the Strivings of the Spirit of God, as the old World did; yea, and as thoſe emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Profeſſors whom <hi>Stephen</hi> reproveth, ſaying, <hi>Ye ſtiff-necked
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102894:14"/>
and uncircumciſed in Heart and Ears, ye do alwayes reſist the Holy Ghoſt; as your Fathers did, ſo do ye,</hi> Acts 7.51.</p>
               <p>And as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which remained Impenitent in the Day of Viſitation, till the Things of her Peace were hid from her Eyes, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.42. And as thoſe Gueſts <hi>which had been often invited, and yet refuſed to come,</hi> making light of thoſe many renew'd and reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Tenders of Grace, <hi>entreating the Meſſengers ſpightfully and ſlew them, wherefore the King was wroth, and protested against them, that none of thoſe Murtherers ſhould taſte of his Supper,</hi> Mat. 22. Or like that <hi>Fig-Tree, which the Maſter of the Vineyard when he had come three Years expecting Fruit and found none, required the Dreſſer to cut it down and caſt it into the Fire,</hi> Luke 13.7. And like <hi>thoſe, who had taſted of the Heavenly Gift, and of the Good Word of God, and of the Powers of the World to come; but after to fall away, and crucifie to themſelves the Son of God afreſh, &amp; put him to open Shame; theſe bringing forth Thorns &amp; Bryars are rejected, and are nigh unto Curſing, whoſe End is to be burned,</hi> Heb. 6.7, 8. And ſuch as the Lord complaineth of by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>They are all grievous Revolters, walking with Slanders; they are Braſs and Iron, they are all Corrupters, the Bellows are burnt, the Lead is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed of the Fire, the Founder melteth in Vain, for the Wicked are not pluck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d away; Reprobate Silver ſhall Men call them, becauſe the Lord hath rejected them,</hi> Jer. 6.29. And the Spirit ſpeaketh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that ſome <hi>ſhall depart from the Faith, giving heed to ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Spirits and Doctrines of Devils, ſpeaking Lyes in Hypocriſie, having their Conſcience ſeared with an Hot Iron, and ſo are paſt fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 1 Tim 4.2. Now if <hi>Reprobates</hi> be taken in this Place for ſuch as God hath given up, caſt off and rejected, yet doth not this prove but the Light of Chriſt was once in them, and at Work in their Hearts: And further, by this Scripture it is manifeſt, that the Light of Chriſt Jeſus is in every Man; And this I know, will ſuffice in Anſwer to ſatisfie the Unprejudiced concerning thoſe Places of Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. The Love of Chriſt conſtraineth us thus to Judge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if Chriſt dyed for all, then were all Dead; and as Chriſt dyed for all, ſo hath this Grace appeared to all; for he hath enlightned all that come into the World, and we know that he is able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſave all that yield Obedience to, and embrace the Tenders of his Boundleſs, Endleſs, Unlimited, Univerſal Love to Mankind
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102894:15"/>
without Exception; and this we are verily perſwaded of from theſe and ſuch like Conſiderations:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe <hi>God is no Reſpecter of Perſons,</hi> Acts 10.35. <hi>He maketh his Sun to riſe on the Evil and the Good, and ſendeth Rain on the Juſt and on the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt; he accepteth not the Perſons of Princes, nor regardeth the Rich more then the Poor; for they all are the Work of his Hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe that Light which ſhined in our Dark, Ignorant, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean and Unbelieving Hearts before Converſion, is the very ſame in which we live and abide ſince our Converſion: That which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſtood by, was an Eye witneſs to, and bore a faithful Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt us while we walked in Darkneſs, is the ſame which ſince the time of our believing and abiding in his Light witneſſeth with our Spirits that we are the <hi>Children of God:</hi> That which cauſed Trouble, Reſtleſneſs and Terror, when we lived in Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, Rebellion and Diſobedience, is the ſame which cauſeth Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Stilneſs, Settlement and Satisfaction, and bringeth forth peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Fruits of Righteouſneſs in our Souls, ſince we have believed &amp; continued obedient thereto: That very <hi>Light</hi> which before convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, reproved, judged &amp; condemned us for all Unbelief and Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs both in Heart &amp; Life, is ſtill the ſame which doth convert, confirm, cleanſe, juſtifie and ſave; yea, that Light which before ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Darkneſs, and the Darkneſs comprehended it not, is but one and the ſame, which after it was believed and obeyed, did expel and lead out of Darkneſs, that the Light which before was ecclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, may now ſo ſhine before Men, that ſeeing our Good Works, may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven; in the Day of their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation: wherefore the Love of Chriſt conſtrains us thus to judge, that the Light of Chriſt is in every Man and Woman, who is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all that believe in him and obey him; becauſe when we were as Vile as the worſt of Sinners, we can witneſs that the ſame Light, which did then ſhine in Darkneſs, doth now, to the Praiſe of God, ſhine out of Darkneſs, whereof we are not aſhamed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe our Lord Jeſus, who cannot Lye, hath ſaid, that man's Condemnation ariſeth only from the Contempt of and Diſobedience to this Light, ſaying, <hi>This is the Condemnation, Light is come into the World, but men love Darkneſs rather then Light,</hi> Jo. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:102894:15"/>
                  <hi>This is (the) the Condemnation that Light is come into the World:</hi> That was only, ſay ſome, <hi>Chriſt's Bodily Preſence upon Earth in that Day;</hi> So then it muſt needs follow, that Condemnation terminated and ended in that Generation, becauſe then that Bodily Preſence expired: But we witneſs according to his own Words, that he is come again in Spirit; for (ſaith he) <hi>They ſhall ſay, Lo here, and Lo there; but go not after them, nor follow them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 17.21, 23, 24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>look not out, for the Kingdom of God is within you: And as the Lightning ſhineth from one Part under Heaven to the other Part under Heaven, ſo ſhall the Son of Man be in his Day; but firſt he muſt ſuffer many Things of this Generation, and be reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted:</hi> We teſtifie therefore, that theſe are the Dayes of the Son of Man; and Chriſt Jeſus the Light, is come into the World, into the Souls &amp; Conſciences of Earthly, VVorldly-minded and Unbelieving Men and VVomen; and they who love Darkneſs rather then Light cannot eſcape Condemnation, becauſe they neglect deſpiſe and reject ſo great Salvation: Therefore as the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> was lift up by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the VVilderneſs even ſo Chriſt Jeſus, the Light of the VVorld, hath God exalted with his own Right Hand, to be a Prince and a Saviour, to give Repentance and Forgiveneſs; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaid, <hi>When he aſcended on high, he led Captivity Captive, and gave Gifts unto Men; now that he aſcended, what is it but that he deſcended firſt into the lower Parts of the Earth; he that deſcended is the ſame alſo which aſcended far above all Heavens,</hi> THAT HE MIGHT FILL ALL THINGS. And thus is his Light in every Man's Conſcience, that they who feel themſelves ſtung by the fiery Serpents in the Wilderneſs of Sin, Darkneſs and Unbelief, and look towards and believe in him, might not periſh, but have Eternal Life; but whoever neglect, overlook or under value this only Saviour of the VVorld, Chriſt Jeſus, the Light, the alone Guide to Reſt, muſt neceſſarily periſh in the VVilderneſs, and dye in their Sins.</p>
               <p>For it is moſt certain, that Man's Damnation muſt undoubtedly ariſe from ſome of theſe Cauſes: (1.) <hi>Either for want of Light:</hi> Or (2.) <hi>From the Deficiency of that Light:</hi> Or (3.) <hi>From man's own Rebellion and Diſobedience to this Light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to judge or believe that man's Condemnation is occaſion'd through the Want of True Saving Light, is horrid Wickedneſs,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102894:16"/>
becauſe it chargeth God fooliſhly with Injuſtice; and nothing leſs then to ſay with the Evil and Unprofitable Servant, <hi>Lord, I know thee to be an Auſtere and Hard Man, reaping where thou haſt not ſown, and gathering where thou haſt not ſtrawed; therefore I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, and went and hid thy Talent in the Earth:</hi> Yea, what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Unmercifulneſs and Injuſtice can be charged upon God, then to ſay or think, <hi>That he hath deſigned any Man's Ruin, and hath denyed him the Benefit of this ſaving Light?</hi> When the Lord hath aſſured Mankind as certainly as he lives, <hi>That he deſires not the Death of any Sinner;</hi> but that this is his Will, and herein he is pleaſed, <hi>That the Wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d might forſake their Wicked Wayes, and live; for he would that all men ſhould be ſaved, and come to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, which Truth is Chriſt, the Light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither can it be granted that man's Condemnation is occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the Inſufficiency of this Light of Chriſt; for, as hath been already proved, <hi>He is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all that come to the Father by him, and is the Mighty Power of God unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> which though in its firſt Appearance be as ſmall as a Grain of Muſtard-ſeed, a Little Leaven, a Bruiſed Reed, or as Smoaking Flax, yet is it that Little Stone, cut out of the Mountains without Hands; yea, though it be rejected, diſallowed, ſet at nought, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and Deſpiſed by all <hi>Babel</hi>'s Builders, as a Poor, Inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Matter: But though theſe <hi>Phraſes</hi> oppoſe the Appearance of Chriſt in Spirit, the Light, &amp; deſpiſe him as the Day of ſmall Things, yet is it the only precious Stone, the tryed Stone, the Corner-ſtone, that ſure Foundation and Rock of Ages, that whoſoever believe and build hereon, the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt them.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſeeing that Light is come into the World, and that the Light Chriſt Jeſus is ſufficient to redeem &amp; ſave all that believe in and obey him; and that Man's Condemnation proceeds only from Diſobedience and Unbelief, in rejecting the Light: It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the earneſt Travail of my Soul, That you, my dear and truly beloved Friends and Relations, may turn in, to the Light in your own Conſciences; retire thither, and wait in the Silence of your own Wills and Wiſdom, for the clear Manifeſtations thereof, then ſhall you know him whom all the VVorld talks of, and need no more that any ſay, <hi>Know the Lord;</hi> for he will reveal himſelf in you: Wherefore as ye love your own Souls, love and cherriſh that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102894:16"/>
in you, which hath ſhewn you the Evil of Sin, the Vanity of this Fading World, and hath been at Work many a time in your Hearts and wrought you into Tenderneſs, panting after Satisfaction from the Living Preſence of God: Oh! Love, believe only in him, hearken only to him, wait continually upon Him, obey, follow and live in his Counſels; fall under his Reproofs with Meekneſs, endure his Judgment with Patience, kiſs the Son leſt he be angry, and ye periſh in the Way; chearfully reſign up your Wills, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, Souls, Bodies, Pleaſures, Profits, Honours, Eſtates, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Life it ſelf, to be univerſally ordered and diſpoſed by him, whoſe Name is Wonderful Counſellor, the Mighty God, the Everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace. This is the Way to True Honour and Durable Riches: Oh therefore be perſwaded to ſtand ſingle in the Teachings, Guidance and Counſels of the Lord Jeſus; Deſpiſe him not; be not aſhamed to own him and his poor Deſpiſed Followers.</p>
               <p>Now, that your Hearts may be carryed above the Snares that attend your Conditions, and be wholely devoted to the Lord, and become Fellow Citizens with the Saints in Light, is the earneſt Breathing and Prayer of him, who is</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Faithful Friend,</hi> James Jackſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:102894:17"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HAving mentioned ſome things before in general, of the Juſt Cauſe of my leaving the <hi>Independent</hi> People, I think it not unſeaſonable to give this particular Account of an Offence receiv'd from the Uneven Walking of <hi>John James,</hi> Paſtor of the <hi>Independents</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> which I ſignified to him before my Forſaking that Way, a Copy whereof followeth, which to this Day ſtands over his Head; for he never returned me an Anſwer to my Letter, but ſtirred up and incenſed my Relations and others againſt me, telling them how greatly I had Injured, Abuſed and Slandered him: <hi>But Wiſdom is juſtified of her Children.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>John James,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Lord knows, and thou art not wholely Ignorant, That ſome years lately paſt my Soul was plunged into a moſt Dreadful State; yea, and I certainly know, that unleſs the moſt precious Sons of <hi>Sion</hi> be kept by the Mighty Power of God, and in themſelves care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerve the firſt Declinings of their Hearts from the Lord, they will be enſnared through the Deceitfulneſs of Sin, and become weak as other Men: And conſider, as thou art in great Danger to be ruin'd, through the Indulgence and Flatteries of thy Brethren (ſome of them ſtyling thee, <hi>The Head of the Church, next and immediately under Chriſt</hi>) and leſt thou ſhouldſt receive Harm for want of Faithfulneſs in Friends watching over thee in Love, I have in Love to thy Soul, and Diſcharge of my Duty, preſented to thy ſerious Conſideration ſome of the things I hear of thee, and partly believe them.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102894:17"/>Whereas heretofore thou uſedſt to preach againſt National Churches, Antichriſt's Clergy, their Covetouſneſs, Pride, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Maintenance, &amp;c. and reprovedſt thy Brethren for hearing thoſe Pariſh Prieſts, with whom now thou art joyned in Combination, to augment thy Eccleſiaſtical Promotions, which before was more Conſiderable then many Parſonages in the County; and ſo thou art leading back again, licking up thy old Vomit; and of late haſt begun in ſeveral Places to Sprinkle Infants.</p>
            <p>That many of thy Poor Brethren, at whoſe Houſes formerly thou kept'ſt Meetings, have now been neglected for above Six Years; but haſt been ever careful to viſit thy kind Benefactors at <hi>Marnham, Skegby, &amp;c.</hi> and very punctual to keep thy Day with the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> at <hi>Nottingham</hi> and <hi>Cheſterfield,</hi> where thou kneweſt thy Pay would be ſweet and certain.</p>
            <p>It was thee only, that after that great Aſſembly was gathered at <hi>Gamſton</hi> by the Labours of ſome private Men, who confined the Work there to a Pack of Clergy-Men, <hi>viz.</hi> Thy Self, <hi>Roſſe, Boſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> and <hi>Clark;</hi> And by the ſame Spirit, and Prelatical Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence ſuſpended old <hi>Allen</hi> (a more Righteous Man then thy ſelf) from Exerciſing in thy Dioces.</p>
            <p>It was the Letter writ with thy own Hand, that obſtructed the intended Marriage betwixt <hi>John Atkinſon</hi> and <hi>Mary Smith;</hi> for although ſeemingly thou pretendedſt Kindneſs to the ſaid <hi>John,</hi> who indeed at the ſame time was in Fellowſhip with thee, yet having Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to a more peculiar Intereſt, ſecretly writ to <hi>Northampton,</hi> and fruſtratedſt the Hopes of the poor Man, which he never Recovered, but Languiſhed and Dyed.</p>
            <p>And when a Letter was written to be ſent to <hi>London,</hi> to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors there, on the behalf of <hi>Robert Johnſon,</hi> a Member of thy Church, to procure his Relief, he being there and Unknown, was exceedingly Diſtreſſed for want of Bread; thou didſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſubſcribe the Letter, and he was Famiſhed and Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102894:18"/>
before that Money got to him which was collected at <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By which it doth appear, that thou haſt lost that Honeſt Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Tenderneſs which once thou didſt ſeem to have, and that the Spirit of God is not thy Guide and Helper; for it hath been ſeriouſly obſerved by thy moſt Judicious Hearers, that thou doſt not bear in thine Aſſemblies a Faithful Teſtimony againſt the Formality, Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, Pride, Bitterneſs and Sinful Compliances of thine Auditors; but daubeſt with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntempered Morter, and preacheſt ſmooth things, Flouriſhes,</hi> Latin <hi>and</hi> Greek <hi>Sentences, and Eloquent Phraſes, to ſet off and beautifie thy Wares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember whence thou art fallen, and Repent; elſe know for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, thou haſt done thy Work, and the Lord will make no more <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of thee; If Salt hath loſt his Savour, it is henceforth good for nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am thine Offended Friend, <hi>James Jackſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
